HEALTH CHECKER
(健康檢查機)
Dad, anal fissure, return quickly.
爸爸 肛裂 速歸
Why is it telling me like it's a telegram?
為什麼是電報啊
And anal fissure?
而且還是肛裂
So,
所以
you said you'd come tomorrow. Why are you here now?
妳明明說明天過來 為什麼現在就出現在這裡了啊
Well…
這個嘛
It all started when my aunt in Takayama
就要從我住在高山的姑姑
gave me something.
送了我某個東西的事開始說起
Something?
某個東西?
LAID-BACK CAMP SEASON 3
《搖曳露營△ (第三季)》
ONE WEEK AGO
(一個禮拜前)
A bicycle?
自行車?
"THE SCENERY FROM MEMORY LANE" Yes.
(第11話 回憶中的風景) 沒錯…
You mentioned you recently started camping, didn't you?
妳不是說妳最近開始露營了嗎
"AUNT FROM TAKAYAMA" I happen to have a bicycle that I'm not using.
(高山的姑姑) 剛好我家有一台沒在用的自行車
It's great for carrying gear
它不僅能載行李
and perfect for camping.
也很適合用在露營
I'll be coming down soon.
最近我有事要去妳們那裡一趟
If you want it, I can bring it to you.
妳要的話 我就順便帶去給妳
A bicycle, huh?
自行車啊
Can I use it to get to school, Aunty?
姑姑 它也能騎去上學嗎
Of course you can! It goes super fast.
可以…而且超快的喔
Super fast you say?
超快的?
A bike made for camping?
適合去露營的自行車
Is it something like that?
是這種的嗎
I've gained quite a bit of weight from all the camp food lately.
拜露營料理所賜 我最近好像胖了不少
I was thinking of starting to bike to school this spring.
正想說春天開始要騎自行車上學呢
Then I'll gladly accept it.
那就恭敬不如從命地收下囉?
All right.
知道了
I'll bring it over on the 1st. Wait for me.
那我一號帶過去 要等我喔
Sure, see you then.
好啦 當天見
Bye.
再見
1ST APRIL AUNT FROM TAKAYAMA 2ND APRIL CHERRY BLOSSOM VIEWING CAMP
(四月一號 高山的姑姑) (四月二號 賞櫻露營)
Time to pack for the cherry blossom viewing camp.
該來準備賞櫻露營的行李了
1ST APRIL
(四月一日)
Aoi-chan, our aunt from Takayama's here.
小葵 高山的姑姑來囉
I'll be right there.
我馬上過去
Aoi-chan!
小葵
How do you like it? Looks cool, right?
怎麼樣 很帥吧
It's a bit different from what I imagined.
總覺得跟我想像中差好多
What's this, Akari-chan?
什麼啊 朱莉
You're still the same height as last time we met.
妳跟上次見面時一模一樣高耶
Wasn't the last time we met during New Year's?
上次見面不是新年的時候嗎
How could I have grown taller in such a short time?
這麼短的時間內 怎麼可能會長高嘛
I'll start growing soon.
我接下來就會長高了
You're about the same height as me, aren't you, Aoi-chan?
小葵應該跟我差不多高吧
Good, good…
很好…
If you were any taller or shorter,
要是身高不一樣
the bike might not fit you as well.
車子可能會跟身體尺寸不合
In this box are the various accessories.
這一箱就是各式各樣的配件
Always make sure you wear a helmet and turn on the front and rear lights.
騎的時候一定要戴安全帽 也要打開前後燈
I've written all the important details on the note.
詳細的注意事項 我都寫在便條紙上了
Make sure to read them before riding.
騎之前要記得看喔
I've given it a basic maintenance check,
我已經幫妳大致上保養過了
but if you have any questions, you can ask Tatsuo.
如果有什麼不懂的 可以問達雄哥
My dad?
爸爸嗎
Yep.
沒錯…
He used to be really into road cycling.
他以前是超熱衷的公路自行車玩家
His legs were as strong as a professional cyclist's.
腿練得跟自行車選手一樣壯
Never heard him talk about that.
都沒聽他說過耶
Well,
那就先這樣
I have things to do now.
姑姑接下來還有事要辦
See you next time.
下次見囉
She left.
走掉了
Aunty is always in such a rush.
姑姑還是那麼急性子呢
Uh-huh.
就是說啊
Aoi-chan, what will you do with the bike?
小葵 這台車要怎麼辦?
Since I'm free today,
反正今天已經沒事了
I'll take it for a spin to the convenience store.
先騎這台去一下超商吧
Can you buy me a bag of crisps? I want the wasabi ones.
那妳幫我買包洋芋片回來 我要山葵口味的
Helmet and lights are set.
安全帽和燈都弄好了
Off we go.
那就出發吧
Feels a bit wobbly.
搖搖晃晃的
Riding this bike makes me nervous even though it's just a bicycle.
明明都是自行車 騎這台卻會莫名緊張耶
Is it because I'm in a different posture?
是因為姿勢不一樣嗎
And compared to my usual bike,
而且跟我平時騎的自行車相比
this one is incredibly light.
這台車簡直輕到不行耶
Let's see…
我看看喔
To shift gears, I need to push the lever on the inside of the brake, right?
變速是要把煞車 靠自己這一側的撥桿往內側撥吧
It got heavier.
變重了
Wow, this thing is super fast!
這是怎樣 速度超快的
Riding it feels so smooth!
騎起來好輕快
You mainly use the right side for shifting.
變速基本上是用右側換
The left side is for steep hills.
左側是遇到陡坡時用的
This feels great!
真舒服
I had my doubts
之前聽到這是"很快的自行車"時
when I heard it was a fast bike,
我還想說自行車就是用人力踩的
since they ultimately rely on human strength.
應該都差不多吧
I stand corrected.
沒想到是這麼一回事
I see, I see. It really is fast.
原來如此 確實很快呢
The brakes are super sensitive!
煞車超靈敏的
If I squeeze too hard, it could be dangerous.
要是握太用力 感覺會很危險呢
Because the brakes are very responsive, be careful while riding.
因為它的煞車很靈敏 騎的時候要小心點
If you brake too hard suddenly,
如果一下子煞過頭
you might flip over, so you need to control the pressure carefully.
還可能會翻車 務必要注意力道
Normally, you hold the top of the handlebars while riding.
平時雖然是握著手把上端騎
But for downhill,
但下坡時為了方便煞車
it's better to grip the lower part to make braking easier.
要改握手把下端騎
Gripping the lower part does give you better control.
握著下端確實比較好施力呢
I wonder how fast this bike can go
這台車
if I pedal with all my strength?
要是盡全力踩的話 能跑到時速幾公里呢?
All right.
好
4-41 kilometres per hour?
四…四十一公里?
That's faster than a moped!
根本比輕型機車還快了吧
But
不過
this is way too scary!
這也太可怕了吧
I should stick to a slower pace.
果然還是慢慢騎吧
Going too fast isn't good for my heart.
騎太快也很危險
Do bicycles have speed limits?
自行車有在限速的嗎
Before I knew it, I'm already at the convenience store.
轉眼間就到超商了
Maybe I should take this a bit further.
果然還是再騎遠一點吧
MINOBU SPECIALITY MANJU
(名產 身延饅頭)
Manju tastes even better when you're tired.
疲憊時吃的饅頭 感覺特別美味呢
I can't believe I cycled all the way to Minobu Station without realising it.
沒想到不知不覺就騎到身延車站了
Speaking of which,
說起來
Aki went ahead to solo camp at the campsite.
明今天好像先去露營場 體驗單人露營了
Is it near Nadeshiko's house?
在撫子家附近嗎
I'll ride all the way to where Aki is!
就一路騎到明那邊吧
…And that's how I ended up here.
所以我就跑來這裡了
It's almost 30 kilometres from your house.
這裡離妳家的距離可是將近30公里
I'm impressed you managed to bike all the way here.
真虧妳能騎自行車過來耶
That's because it's lighter than a regular bike,
那是因為它比普通的自行車還輕
making it easier to ride.
騎起來挺輕鬆的
Even though I got tired,
雖然還是會累
it was still a manageable distance.
但也不是沒辦法騎到的距離
But my butt
不過
is a little sore.
屁股倒是有點痛
So this is the bike.
這就是那台自行車啊
It looks pretty cool.
看起來挺帥的嘛
The handlebars sort of look like Caribou-kun's antlers.
總覺得它的手把 有點像卡力布君的角
Now that you mention it, they do resemble them a bit.
聽妳這麼一說 確實有點像呢
Right?
對啊
Well, I should get going.
那麼 我差不多該啟程了
It'll take some time to ride back home.
畢竟騎到家需要一點時間
Don't want to be out there when it's dark.
要是沒趁天黑之前回去 感覺也很危險
You're right.
說得也是
Be careful on your way back.
路上小心喔
Oh no, a flat tire!
居然爆胎了
What… what should I do now?
這…這下該怎麼辦啊
TAKABAYASHI MEATS
(肉之高林)
Lamb can be a bit gamey, and some people don't like it.
羊肉會有腥味 而且也有人不喜歡
Better buy two portions of pork and one portion of lamb.
還是買兩份豬肉 和一份羊肉比較好吧
Assuming 200 grams per person,
假設一人200克
"CHERRY BLOSSOM VIEWING CAMP MEMBERS" for six people, that's 1200 grams.
(賞櫻露營成員) 六人份就是1200克
So we need 400 grams of lamb and 800 grams of pork.
所以要買400克羊肉 800克豬肉
No, wait…
不對
This is delicious!
真好吃
Kagamihara-san alone could probably eat around 400 grams.
各務原同學一個人 恐怕就能吃400克左右
In that case…
這樣的話
And Akari-chan will probably join us too.
朱莉應該也會一起來吧?
The others will take care of the vegetables.
蔬菜類是交給大家負責
All that's left is the sauce and…
接著就只剩醬料跟…
This… this meat is…
這…這個肉是…
Got it. After six, right?
我知道了 六點之後對吧?
Sorry about the trouble.
不好意思 那就拜託你了
My dad said he'd come pick me up in the van after work.
我爸說他下班後 會開廂型車來接我
Luckily, your family's got a spacious car.
幸好妳家的車很大
Well then, just sit down and relax until he comes to get you.
那麼 在叔叔來接妳前 就坐下來好好放鬆一下吧
Thank you. I'll do just that.
那我就恭敬不如從命了
So spicy! Super spicy!
好辣 超辣的
But… it's really tasty.
不…不過很好喝耶
Dilute it a little and it'll be perfect.
再稀釋一下 味道就會剛剛好囉
Hey,
欸
why doesn't that bike have a kickstand?
為什麼那台自行車沒有側柱啊
I looked it up.
這個我有查過
Apparently, these types of bikes don't have them to keep the weight down.
聽說這種自行車為了減輕重量 都不會裝側柱
So if you don't park it properly
所以要是沒停好
and the tires move a bit, it could topple over.
輪胎動一下就有可能倒在地上
Even if you're just stopping briefly, you have to be careful.
即便只是稍微停一下 也得小心點才行呢
In that case,
既然如此
how about using this strap
就用這條這麼做
to keep the brakes engaged?
讓車子保持煞車狀態怎麼樣?
That way, the tires won't move. That's a good idea.
這樣輪胎就不會動了 確實是個好主意
But what's this strap?
不過這條是什麼啊
I made it earlier to pass the time.
這是我剛才做來打發時間的
It's called a paracord bracelet.
叫做傘繩手環
Making ginger ales and bracelets.
又是調薑汁汽水 又是做手環
You sure are enjoying the solo camp life.
妳還挺享受獨自露營的嘛
You can have it if you need.
既然妳用得上 就拿走吧
Can I?
可以嗎
I bought a 30-metre roll anyway. There's still plenty left.
反正我買了一捲30公尺的傘繩 現在還剩很多
I can whip up another in no time.
馬上就能再做一條了
Sounds like you could make a lot of bracelets.
30公尺感覺可以做很多條呢
Well then,
那麼
I shall gratefully use this.
我就恭敬不如從命 心懷感激地使用囉
This is such a quiet and nice campsite.
這裡真是個安靜又不錯的露營場呢
Right?
對吧
A handmade paracord bracelet
自製的傘繩手環
can sell for around 1,000 yen each.
一條可以賣一千圓左右耶
Quite a lot of people are selling them online.
網拍上還滿多人在賣的喔
Seriously?
真的假的
I suppose I should charge you 1,000 yen then.
果然還是算妳一千圓吧
Nope. It's mine already.
不要…我已經收下了
Please reconsider.
拜託考慮一下嘛
The cherry blossoms here are spectacular too!
這裡的櫻花也很壯觀呢
They say they're 300 years old.
聽說它的樹齡有300年喔
After 300 years, you'd figure they could use some support.
既然已經站了300年 肯定會想要個支柱吧
They've been standing for 300 years after all.
畢竟站了300年嘛
Jiunji Temple.
慈雲寺
"JIUNJI TEMPLE" Doesn't "Jiunji Temple"
(慈雲寺) 不覺得"慈雲寺"這三個字
just make you want to say it out loud?
會讓人很想說出口嗎
Jiunji Temple.
慈雲寺
What's with this photo?
這張是怎樣啊?
So, you drove to all these places to see the cherry blossoms.
原來妳們開車到這麼多地方賞櫻啊
Rin-chan, you took a lot of pictures too.
小凜也拍了很多照片呢
Oh, it's the fruit park!
是水果公園
Did you go solo camping yesterday?
妳昨天是去單人露營嗎
-Yes. -That parfait looks delicious!
-是的 -聖代看起來好好吃喔
I went to the mountains in Fujikawacho this time.
我這次去富士川町的山區那一帶
There were lots of cherry blossoms blooming. It was pretty nice.
那邊開了許多櫻花 還挺不錯的
And there's a hot spring on a cliff nearby.
而且附近還有個建在峭壁上的溫泉
That was pretty interesting.
很有趣喔
I'll have to check it out next time.
我下次也去去看吧
Can you give me the address?
可以告訴我地址嗎
Here's our house-made baked custard pudding.
這是各位點的本店自製硬式烤布丁
Thank you.
謝謝
Homemade baked custard pudding.
自製硬式烤布丁
This pudding looks firm.
這布丁真穩固呢
Let's dig in.
我要開動了
Vanilla ice cream drizzled with caramel
淋了焦糖的香草冰淇淋
paired with an egg-rich, baked custard pudding.
配上蛋香濃郁的硬式烤布丁
It has such a simple, comforting taste.
真是樸素又令人安心的味道啊
This pudding has a wonderful texture!
這個布丁吃起來很有嚼勁 感覺真不錯呢
It's like eating firm grilled tofu.
硬度跟烤豆腐差不多呢
It does feel like grilled tofu.
確實很像烤豆腐呢
All you took pictures of at Katsunuma Station
妳在勝沼車站那邊
were just the trains.
根本沒在拍櫻花 都在拍電車吧
Well, they had those retro trains, so I got carried away…
因為那邊有復古電車 不小心就…
Speaking of which,
話說回來
besides Katsunuma,
我記得除了勝沼之外
I think there are some parks in Fujikawacho
富士川町還有一些公園
that also have retro trams.
也會擺放復古的路面電車喔
Really?
真的嗎
It's probably this place, Fujikawa Nagasawa Park.
應該是這個富士川長澤公園吧
Such cute, retro trams!
是復古又可愛的路面電車耶
Apparently, Kofu used to have trams running as well.
據說甲府以前 也有路面電車在行駛喔
And,
還有
in Nirasaki, there's a park that has steam locomotives.
韮崎那邊好像也有公園 會展示蒸氣列車
Steam locomotives as well?
連蒸氣電車都有嗎
Fujii Park in Nirasaki
韮崎藤井公園
not only has steam locomotives and electric locomotives on display,
不僅有展示蒸氣列車和電力機關車
but it also has mini steam locomotives running.
甚至還有迷你蒸氣列車在裡面行駛
What kind of park is that?
這到底是什麼公園啊
Sakura, can we…
姊姊 等一下…
It's late.
現在都已經晚上了
Let's leave that for another day.
改天再去吧
Did you take this in Isawa?
這是在石和拍的嗎
I took this picture because the mountain had a pattern that looked like
因為山上印著形似鳥居的圖案
a torii gate on it.
所以就拍了一下
But what exactly is this?
不過這到底是什麼東西啊
It's called Oigatayaki.
這叫做笈形燒
Oigatayaki?
笈形燒?
I was just about to go see it.
我接下來正打算去看
Want to come along?
妳們要一起來嗎
Sakura?
姊姊?
The view here is really nice.
這裡景色真不錯呢
Rin-chan,
小凜
where can we see the Oigatayaki?
要在哪邊才看得到笈形燒呢?
Let me think.
我想想喔
It should be near that mountain.
應該是在那座山附近吧
Starting on April 1st, they light up torii gate-shaped fires here
每年的四月一號開始 這裡就會連續幾天
every evening for a few days.
在晚上點起鳥居形狀的燈火喔
But actually, it's not a torii gate,
不過準確來說 應該不是鳥居
it's more like an "oi".
而是"笈"才對
"Oi"?
笈?
I'm not exactly sure about the details.
詳細內容我也不太清楚就是了
Oigatayaki,
笈形燒
a bonfire shaped like the "oi" that ascetics carry on their backs.
是一種以修驗者背的"笈" 為造型的篝火
In the Heian period,
平安時代
there was a severe conflict between Daizenji in Koshu
甲州的大善寺與笛吹的長谷寺之間
and Chokokuji in Fuefuki.
發生了嚴重的鬥爭
"CHOKOKUJI, DAIZENJI" Ready…
(長谷寺 大善寺) 預備
Fight!
開始
The conflict was so intense that it resulted in deaths,
由於其鬥爭嚴重到出現死者
prompting Yamanashioka Shrine to join Chokokuji's side
看不下去的山梨岡神社 就加入了長谷寺那邊
to try and calm things down.
試圖平息紛爭
However, this only angered the monks of Daizenji,
然而此舉卻激起了 大善寺僧侶的怒火
who retaliated by stealing and burning the torii gate of Yamanashioka Shrine.
並在一氣之下 把山梨岡神社的鳥居搶來燒了
The monks of Chokokuji, in turn,
看到此事的長谷寺僧侶也非常生氣
became furious and burned Daizenji's oi as revenge.
因此燒掉大善寺的笈作為報復
That's the origin of Fuefuki's Oigatayaki
據說這就是笛吹的笈形燒
and Koshu's torii gate burning.
以及甲州的鳥居燒的由來
That's a dark story…
居然起源自這麼嚇人的事件嗎
I thought it would be a more festive story.
我還以為會是什麼 更有祭典氣氛的故事呢
History is often like that.
歷史大多都是這樣的啦
Even the warlords of the Sengoku period are seen as heroes today.
那些戰國武將 如今也被世人當作英雄看待啊
Apparently, since the Edo period,
聽說從江戶時代開始
people have been lighting these fires to send off spirits.
人們就已經把這當作 送別亡靈的篝火在點了
I see…
這樣啊
Since people still light the Oigatayaki,
既然現在還有人在點笈形燒
does that mean the torii gate burning still happens?
所以鳥居燒也仍然存在著嗎
The torii gate burning happens in October.
鳥居燒是每年十月進行的
In fact,
話說回來
it's actually right behind you.
它其實就在妳的正後方喔
So, we're directly below where the torii gate burning takes place.
原來這裡是鳥居燒的正下方啊
It seems that the Oigatayaki is now done with lights.
笈形燒現在好像改用照明燈了
But the torii gate burning is still done with wood, just like in the past.
不過鳥居燒還是和過去一樣 會燒柴來點亮篝火
Koshu's torii gate burning is an event held in early October.
甲州的鳥居燒是十月上旬的活動
Local middle school volunteers
會由當地的國中生志工
carry firewood up the slope of Mount Kashioyama,
在柏尾山的山坡上推起木柴
and on the day of the torii gate burning,
並於鳥居燒當天
they run through the town with torches lit from Daizenji,
拿著從大善寺取火的火把 在鎮上奔走
eventually lighting the torii gate
最後跑到山上
on the mountain.
點亮鳥居燒
Middle schoolers sure are energetic.
國中生好活躍啊
It does sound intriguing.
不過 聽起來滿有趣的呢
I wonder if we could do something like that while camping?
不知道露營時 能不能也像這樣玩一次
The moment you start running around the campsite with a torch,
在妳拿起火把在露營場 到處跑的瞬間就會被趕出去了吧
By the way, Rin-chan, do you come here often?
是說 小凜經常來這裡嗎
I used to come a lot when I was a kid.
小時候滿常來的
Every spring, my family would go cherry blossom viewing,
每年一到春天 我們家都會出門賞櫻
have dinner in Kofu,
在甲府吃完晚餐後
and then come here to see the Oigatayaki.
就會來這裡眺望笈形燒
I see.
這樣啊
Even though it's been a long time
明明已經很久沒來了
and I didn't ride here myself back then,
而且當時也不是自己騎車來的
I still remember the way.
沒想到我還記得怎麼走呢
So, this is a view from Rin-chan's memories.
原來這是小凜回憶中的風景啊
18:59.
18點59分
Almost time for the lights to come on.
差不多快到點燈時間了呢
There it is!
在那裡
See you tomorrow, Rin-chan.
那就明天見囉 小凜
See you tomorrow at the cherry blossom viewing camp.
明天賞櫻露營的時候見
Sakura-san,
櫻小姐
are you taking the highway back?
您回去是走高速公路嗎
Yes, since we're close to the Katsunuma interchange.
對 因為這裡離勝沼交流道很近
They should be lighting up the Daimonji tonight.
今天應該也會點大文字燒
You should be able to see it on the left side on the way back.
回程途中應該能在左側看見
Thank you, I'll keep an eye out.
謝謝妳 我會注意的
Since Sakura will be driving,
因為姊姊要開車
I'll make sure to capture it perfectly.
我會負責把它完美拍下來的
Drive safely, Rin-chan!
路上小心喔 小凜
All right. We're leaving.
好了 要走囉
Okay.
好
The night view of the basin really is beautiful.
盆地的夜景果然很漂亮呢
Haven't you had your fill of the torii gate burning earlier?
剛才在鳥居燒那邊 應該已經看夠了吧
Watching it from the car has its own charm, doesn't it?
從車裡看出去的風景 又別有一番風味嘛
We must be getting close to the Daimonji that Rin-chan mentioned.
差不多快到小凜說的大文字燒了吧
You might miss it.
妳這樣會錯過喔
I know.
我知道啦
There's Daimonji!
看到大文字燒了
This is…
妳這是…
…more like "Omonji".
才文字燒吧
If we were a bit further away,
如果距離再遠一點
I could have gotten a better shot.
就能拍得更好了
Then let's come back next year during cherry blossom season.
那我們明年賞櫻季再來吧
I'm saved!
得救了
Thanks for coming to pick me up right after work.
謝謝你一下班就過來載我
No worries.
沒事啦
But I'm impressed, Aoi.
不過 葵
It's your first time riding on a road bike
真虧妳第一次騎公路車
and you went so far.
就騎到那麼遠的地方呢
You were a road cyclist too, weren't you, Dad?
不過爸爸以前也是 公路自行車玩家吧
How far have you ridden before?
你最遠騎到哪裡呀?
I've only done cross-country biking for commuting.
爸爸以前只有在通勤時 會騎越野單車喔
But Aunty said…
可是姑姑說…
What's the date today?
今天幾月幾號?
Pranked you!
騙妳的
She got you.
妳被騙了呢
I completely forgot it's April 1st today!
都忘記今天是四月一號了
NEXT EPISODE: 2ND APRIL CHERRY BLOSSOM VIEWING CAMP
(下集 四月二號 賞櫻露營)
WHEN ENJOYING CAMPING, BE SURE TO FOLLOW THE RULES
(享受露營時…) (務必遵守露營場和其設施的規定)
DON'T FORGET TO PUT OUT YOUR CAMPFIRE AND DISPOSE OF YOUR GARBAGE.
(別忘了滅火和帶走垃圾)
TEMPERATURES CAN CHANGE QUICKLY, SO CHECK THE WEATHER FORECAST BEFOREHAND.
(由於氣溫可能會急速變化) (記得事先確認天氣預報)
WEAR WARM CLOTHING IF NECESSARY TO PREVENT COLD.
(必要時穿著保暖衣物防寒)